Guide to the Records of the National Jewish Welfare Board, undated, 1889-1995 (bulk 1917-1990) *I-337
American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA and New York, NY
Qualified rabbis were also in short supply during the 1960s. As opposition to the war in Vietnam increased, the Commission on Jewish Chaplaincy (CJC) intensified its recruitment efforts and continued to recruit lay leaders to carry on religious and educational programs for Jewish servicemen. To help alleviate the shortage of chaplains, in 1966, JWB developed a retention plan that encouraged rabbis to make the military chaplaincy a career. In 1969 the CJC began recruiting chaplains among rabbis holding civilian positions. JWB also helped organize regional conferences of Jewish chaplains, community leaders, JCC staff, and regional consultants to help develop a better understanding of the needs of servicemen.
At the close of the 1960s JWB offered an energetic program that detected new social work needs, charted new directions, and pioneered new advances in social work practice. JWB's Service to Small Communities program began offering services to small and isolated Jewish communities throughout the country. It developed new programs to serve Jewish college youth and learn more about the attitudes, needs, and interests of the college generation. More intensive programming in Jewish music, drama, graphic arts, theatre, and dance were encouraged. And finally, displays of American Jewish history were developed and viewed by thousands in the Centers.
Many of the programs and policies of JWB were shaped to a large degree by the increasing racial confrontation and social and political turmoil of the 1960s. Rising anti-Semitism in the black community led to an examination of how JCCs could contribute to an improvement in black-white relationships. As a result, the Centers began many social, recreational, and cultural programs in urban areas. These programs included tutorial and remedial reading classes, Center day and resident camps for the poor, head start programs, and child-care centers. Although most of these programs were offered to disadvantaged blacks, Puerto Ricans, Mexican-Americans, and impoverished Jews also participated. Center activities on behalf of the poor and disenfranchised reflected the belief of the majority of the Jewish community that Jews had a moral and economic interest in eliminating the causes of racial disorder and poverty.
The development of links overseas continued to grow, particularly after the Six-Day War in 1967. The fate of Israel found a place in the hearts and minds of the Jewish people and the JCCs were infused with a new energy. They helped organize, direct, and motivate Jewish support for the state of Israel. JWB expertise was used to train staff in Israeli centers.
Overseas links to Europe and other areas around the world were nurtured by JWB's international consultation program. JWB and Center professionals contributed to the planning and workshops of the International Conference of Jewish Communal Service in Jerusalem. Finally, JWB helped support outdoor Center demonstrations in support of Soviet Jewry.
The JCCs respond to a changing Society
Like most of America, the JWB and JCC movement was swept up in the societal changes of the 1970s and 1980s. The Jewish community faced a rise in alternative household arrangements that had little connection to the synagogue or JCC movement. Many Jews were single or divorced with children and a growing number were over the age of fifty. Moreover, the trend of intermarriage, assimilation, and lower births threatened the long-term survival of the Jewish community. As a result of these changes, JWB began to develop new cultural and educational programs to strengthen the Jewish community.
Various counseling, single parent support groups, and recreational activities were started by JWB in response to the changing family environment. Programs were also developed for the homebound elderly, Jewish children unaffiliated with Jewish organizations, and older adults. Children, adults, and families were encouraged to explore their Jewish heritage and culture and to join synagogues and temples.
As the 1980s progressed, fathering programs were designed to assist men as they took on additional parenting responsibilities at home. New day care programs for the elderly and horticultural therapy were offered to senior citizens. A Shalom Newcomers Network was begun to help Jewish families and individuals put down Jewish roots in new communities. By the end of the decade, the JCCs had developed a wide array of programs to deal with such everyday concerns as heart disease prevention, child abuse, and AIDS prevention.
JWB reinforced its long-term commitment to Jewish education during the 1980s. To help the JCCs reach their full educational potential, in 1983 the Commission on Maximizing Jewish Education in Jewish Community Centers was given the task of studying Jewish educational programming. As a result of this study, new programs designed to stimulate Jewish awareness, knowledge, and identification were introduced into the JCCs. A wide range of educational activities for young and old, men and women, were established throughout the JCCs to enrich Jewish life and deepen their sense of Jewish identity and commitment.
Foreign contacts continued and expanded with Jews in Venezuela, Canada, France, Israel, and in the Soviet Union. The JCCs celebrated the 30th anniversary of Israeli's founding with special expos, walk-a-thons, music and dance programs, presentations, and athletic events. By 1979, there were ninety-one community centers in the Jewish State. JWB recognized the importance of its Israel connection when, in 1980, it helped sponsor the Israel Desk Program. This program was developed to encourage North American Jews to go to Israel to work, study, perform voluntary services, or perhaps to settle. It was aimed at making Israel more accessible to American Jewry.
The influx of Russian Jews into the United States propelled the development of special JWB programs to ease the pains of readjustment. New programs in housing, healthcare, and legal rights were developed to help assimilate the new immigrants, and special classes in the reading and writing of English were also offered.
New Directions and Programs
In 1990 JWB, in order to more accurately reflect the organization's mission and goals, and its connection with the Jewish Community Center movement, changed its name to the Jewish Community Centers Association of North America (JCC Association). The JCC Association resolved to become more proactive in anticipating the needs of the Jewish community and in providing the mechanisms and resources to meet those needs.
The 1990s witnessed the introduction of new programs and relationships overseas. A summer teen experience in Israel was launched, which emphasized education and leadership skills. In addition, executive training for Israeli staff was expanded and included graduate level courses focusing on Jewish issues within the context of Israel. An Israeli Fellowship Program and leadership training seminars were also offered. In 1999, the JCC Association began the Birthright Israel program, which sponsored first-time visits to Israel for American Jews. In the same year, the JCC Maccabi Xperience was started for high school and college students and for young professionals up to the age of 33. Maccabi programs included visits to cultural, historical, and geographical sites throughout Israel.
The JCC Association also began to help rebuild Jewish communities in the former Soviet Union. Since most Russian Jews had little or no exposure to the Jewish religion, the JCC movement primarily concentrated on building connections to Jewish communities. JCC programs stressed the promotion of Jewish culture, education, and Jewish life. By 1997 thirty-eight JCCs were in operation in Russia.
At home, the JCC Association continued the development of various programs to meet the needs of the Jewish community. Early childhood programs were promoted in the Centers, Young Judaea Clubs were started, and teen leadership summits, exploring such issues as respect, tolerance, and conflict resolution, were begun. The JCCs continued to stress the development of educational opportunities for its members. Programs to better educate and train lay leaders were started; scholarship and fellowship programs for teenagers were introduced; and an endowment was funded to bring world-class Jewish scholars to JCC conferences. Finally, continental standards to help measure JCC performances in meeting the goals of the movement were developed, covering everything from Jewish education programs to the safe storage of supplies.
With the beginning of the new century, the JCC Association had gone high tech. It launched an online resource for Jewish early childhood educators and created an Internet service so that JCC professionals could interact with each other more efficiently. In addition, the JCC Association continued to develop innovative programming for the Jewish community. For instance, programs were established to educate and train JCC staff in integrating disabled youth into center activities. The JCC Association and the National Foundation of Jewish Culture helped create the Jewish Council for the Arts to promote Jewish art and culture. To reflect the growing needs of adults over fifty years old, a JCC task force began the development of new and modern adult programming. Additionally, a JCC North America Kallah program was begun to provide focused, high profile, and exciting adult Jewish programming. In the year 2000, the JCC Association Center for Jewish Education was started with the goal of providing on-going training and development for JCC professionals. This new educational association serves as a resource for Jewish educators and provides them with guidance in the development of Center education initiatives.
The new century finds the JCC Association continuing to adapt, innovate, and refine its vision of the future. Like its predecessors, the goal of the JCC Association is to strengthen the bonds of the Jewish community. Thus, the theme of the 2000 Biennial was "Building Meaningful Jewish Community" and it found over 1000 lay leaders, board members, presidents and executives from JCCs across North America examining their past, debating plans for the future, and demonstrating the commitment of the JCC movement to American Jewry.
Bibliography
Bernstein, Philip S. Rabbis at War: The CANRA Story. Waltham, Massachusetts: The American Historical Society, 1971.
Dobkowski, Michael N., ed. Jewish American Voluntary Organizations. Westport, Connecticut: Greenwood Press, Inc., 1986.
Janowsky, Oscar I., Louis Kraft and Bernard Postal. Change and Challenge: A History of 50 Years of the JWB. New York: National Jewish Welfare Board, 1966.
Janowsky, Oscar I. The JWB Survey. New York: The Dial Press, 1948.
Kaufman, Isidor. American Jews in World War II: The Story of 550,000 Fighters for Freedom. New York: Dial Press, 1947.
Korn, Bertram W. Centennial of the Jewish Chaplaincy in the United States, 1862-1962. New York: The American Jewish Historical Society, 1962.
Kraft, Louis. A Century of the Jewish Community Center Movement. New York: National Jewish Welfare Board, 1953.
Jewish Community Centers Association of North America, Annual Reports: 1996, 1997, 1999, 2000. New York: JCC Association, 1996-1997, 1999-2001
JCC Circle, Fall 2000 - Summer 2001.
Jewish Community Centers Association website: http://www.jcca.org
JWB Circle, November 1979-Summer 1986.
Unfortunately, there are no full-length contemporary studies of the Jewish Welfare Board or the Jewish Community Center movement, and the Board does not seem to have published any annual reports from 1970 to the mid-1990s. Therefore, researchers should consult the JCC Association's website (http://www.jcca.org) and the serial publications The JWB Circle and The JCC Circle for more current information about the Jewish Community Center movement.
Chronology
1917 JWB organized in New York City, April 9, to serve religious and welfare needs of Jewish military personnel in World War I. The conference convened by National Council of YMHAs and Kindred Associations names Dr. Cyrus Adler President.
1917 United States Government Commission on Training Camp Activities names JWB as Jewish community's instrument for serving military. JWB begins recruiting Rabbis as Chaplains and hundreds of field workers.
1917 Commissioning of Jewish chaplains authorized by Congress at JWB's behest.
1917 Colonel Harry Cutler succeeds Dr. Adler as JWB President.
1918 JWB opens servicemen's Centers for Jewish soldiers at domestic and overseas posts, making extensive use of YM-YWHA buildings.
1918 JWB becomes part of United War Work Campaign.
1918 200 Jewish communities organized for war service.
1918 National Association of Jewish Center Workers founded, with Aaron Robison as first President.
1919 Registration and identification of Jewish war graves overseas undertaken by JWB.
1919 Welfare needs of demobilized servicemen handled by JWB.
1920 War Department asks JWB to continue morale services for peacetime military.
1921 Merger with National Council of YMHAs and Kindred Associations, founded in 1913, makes JWB national association of Ys and JCCs and agency for serving Jews in military as of July 1.
1921 New England, New Jersey, New York State and Pennsylvania Federations of YM-YWHAs and Metropolitan New York League of Jewish Community Associations, all antedating JWB, become part of new organization.
1921 Judge Irving Lehman elected President.
1921 Community studies and building fund campaign undertaken for new JCCs.
1921 First training course for JCC workers established.
1922 JWB begins intensive programming services to JCCs. Lecture Bureau organized and Jewish Center Quarterly Launched.
1922 Building Bureau established for JCCs.
1922 Welfare and religious services extended to Canal Zone.
1923 Jewish Welfare Trust created from surplus of World War I funds.
1925 President Coolidge joins JWB leaders in laying cornerstone of Washington, D.C., Center.
1925 Veterans' Administration recognizes JWB as agency to present claims of Jewish veterans.
1925 47 new JCC buildings opened since end of war, bringing total to 120.
1925 JWB helps create Graduate School for Jewish Social Work in New York.
1926 Religious and welfare services extended to citizen military training camps.
1926 JWB cooperates with American Battle Monuments Commission in marking Jewish war graves.
1927 JWB convenes first training institute for JCC workers.
1928 JWB joins Amateur Athletic Union and U.S. Olympic Committee as representative of Jewish Community in amateur sports.
1929 JCCs become rallying points for protests against Arab riots in Palestine.
1929 Stock Market crash brings halt to decades of new JCC building construction.
1930 JWB helps form National Conference on Jewish Employment.
1931 JWB Salon in Pershing World War I Memorial Hall in Paris dedicated.
1932 Day Camp programming for JCCs launched by JWB.
1932 First National Center Basketball Tournament and Air Mail Track Meet held.
1932 JWB joins President Hoover's Welfare and Relief Mobilization.
1932 JWB organizes American team for first Maccabiad in Palestine.
1933 JWB helps launch mobilization for human needs under National Recovery Administration.
1934 Department of Health Education and Camping established. JWB holds first camp counselors training course.
1935 JWB and Centers organize American team for Palestine Maccabiad.
1936 JWB leads fight to keep United States out of Nazi-controlled Berlin Olympic Games.
1936 Personnel Department is organized.
1936 Eleven societies on the West Coast organize the Pacific Coast Federation of JCCs, which is admitted into JWB two years later.
1937 Expanding Center movement pays tribute to JWB on 20th anniversary at annual convention.
1938 JWB spurs Centers to aid in assistance of refugees from Hitlerism.
1938 JWB helps organize National Jewish Committee on Scouting.
1939 Adoption of Mobilization Day Plan prepares JWB for wartime role.
1940 War Department reaffirms JWB role as official representative of Jewish Community in serving military.
1940 Expanded Committee on Army and Navy Religious Activities begins recruiting Jewish chaplains to meet mounting needs of Armed Forces.
1940 Jewish Community Center Program Aids launched.
1940 Frank L. Weil elected President.
1941 JWB becomes a founding member of USO.
1941 Hundreds of Jewish Communities mobilize for war service under JWB Banner.
1941 JWB given responsibility for compiling record of Jewish military participation.
1942 Organization of Jewish Community Center Division spurs service to Center field.
1942 President Roosevelt lauds JWB on 25th anniversary for service to nation and communities.
1942 Women's Organizations' Division created for war service.
1942 JWB begins overseas operations for Armed Forces.
1942 JWB helps establish Associated Youth Organizations, alliance of six national agencies, to map joint action on youth needs.
1943 JWB serves military on five continents through chaplains, field workers, community groups, and USO.
1943 JWB becomes constituent of Greater New York United Jewish Appeal.
1944 Jewish Chaplains at side of GIs as European invasion begins.
1944 Overseas Army and Navy Committees established.
1944 JWB becomes sponsor of Jewish Book Council of America.
1944 Southern Section of JWB is organized.
1944 USO-JWB programs for military help generate Jewish activities in small Jewish communities.
1945 War's end finds JWB serving in 588 communities and at 203 USO operations; 311 Jewish chaplains on duty.
1945 JWB organizes National Jewish Music Council and launches Jewish Music Festival.
1945 Independent survey of JWB to guide postwar programming and service initiated, with Dr. Salo W. Baron as head of survey commission and Dr. Oscar I. Janowsky as survey Director.
1945 Jewish chaplains aid liberated concentration camp survivors.
1946 President Truman pays tribute to JWB's wartime services.
1946 JWB takes initiative in creating World Federation of YMHAs.
1946 Women's Organizations' Division launches Serve-a-Hospital Program.
1946 JWB Circle is born as Jewish Center Quarterly suspends publication.
1947 JWB Survey calls for stressing Jewish goals and programs of Centers. Adoption of survey recommendations ushers in new era for Center movement.
1947 "Americans in World War II," story of Jewish wartime heroism, by Dr. Samuel C. Kohs and I. Kaufman, published by JWB.
1947 JWB joins in creating Training Bureau for Jewish communal service.
1947 Jewish Music Council sponsors international competition for new compositions.
1948 JWB becomes sponsor of American Jewish Historical Society.
1948 Louis Kraft goes to Israel during Arab siege to set up Jerusalem YMHA.
1948 JWB takes part in reconstituted USO, as new selective Service Act becomes law.
1948 National Jewish Youth Conference founded under JWB auspices.
1948 Centers become focal points of community celebrations hailing birth of State of Israel.
1949 Center and Synagogue relationships explored by JWB and Synagogue Council of America.
1949 First Jewish History Week is observed.
1949 JWB joins Veterans Administration Voluntary Service Program.
1950 Rabbis vote self-imposed draft to recruit military chaplains.
1950 JWB helps form Associated Services for Armed Forces as USO deactivates.
1950 Jerusalem YM-YWHA opened as first center in Israel.
1950 Irving Edison elected President as Frank L. Weil retires.
1950 JWB creates Frank L. Weil Awards in three areas of service.
1951 President Truman tells JWB "Morale is your job, Keep it up!"
1951 USO called back into service with JWB representing Jewish community.
1951 Center Programs for aged expand under JWB impetus.
1952 First JWB Year Book is issued.
1952 New GI Haggadah published by Chaplaincy Commission.
1952 JWB helps create council on Social Work Education.
1952 American Jewish Historical Society again becomes independent society.
1953 JWB sponsors observance of Jewish Community Center Centennial.
1953 Nationwide drive to recruit Center workers launched by JWB.
1953 JWB Servicemen's Club opens in Tokyo.
1953 Ford Foundation grant helps train European Center workers in United States.
1954 JWB program resources used in American Jewish Tercentenary Celebration.
1954 President Eisenhower urges JWB to maintain morale services to military.
1954 First book on Center practice published by NAJCW and JWB.
1954 Commission on Center-Federation Relationships created.
1954 Charles Aaron elected President.
1955 Religious school curriculum for GI's children published by Chaplaincy Commission.
1956 President Eisenhower hails JWB role in building good citizenship.
1956 JWB Associates is launched.
1957 Personnel at newly opened missile bases get JWB morale services.
1957 Scholarship program expanded for qualified young people seeking careers in Center work.
1957 National Jewish Writers Conference sponsored by Jewish Book Council.
1958 Sabbath Programming Policy for Centers is adopted.
1958 Jewish Chaplains on scene as Middle East crisis erupts.
1958 Code to promote Center-Federation ties approved.
1958 Lloyd W. Dinkelspiel elected President.
1959 Jewish values in Center programming appraised at JWB conference.
1959 Chaplaincy Commission prepares Jewish section in Tri-Faith Hymnal.
1959 First National Training Institute held for Center women leaders.
1959 Solomon Litt elected President on death of Lloyd W. Dinkelspiel.
1960 Centers assume role in JWB financing with the adoption of Fair Share Plan at JWB Biennial.
1960 JWB joins Council of Cultural Agencies.
1960 JWB takes active role in White House Conference on Children and Youth.
1961 Broad reappraisal of JWB structure and services is launched.
1961 Findings of JWB Study on Teenagers is published.
1961 New military buildup spurs call for more Jewish chaplains and JWB service.
1961 National Public Affairs Committee established.
1961 JWB participates in White House Conference on Aging.
1961 JWB Year Book reports that 83 new Centers erected since end of war have cost $80,000,000.
1961 S.D. Gershovitz Memorial Young Adult Research Project started.
1962 Major JWB structural and service changes begin as reappraisal report is adopted.
1962 Centennial of Jewish Military Chaplaincy.
1962 Cuban crisis brings swift JWB mobilization.
1962 JWB aids Canadian Ys to form National Council.
1962 National Conference on Center Programming in the Arts convened.
1963 JWB Research Center established in cooperation with NAJCW.
1963 Domestic Peace Corps and U.S. Cultural Arts Program endorsed by JWB.
1963 Dedication of Air Force Academy Chapel equipped through JWB efforts.
1963 JWB enunciates supportive position on Civil Rights and urges Centers to follow suit.
1963 Consolidation of regional center and Armed Services work begins.
1963 JWB joins in observance of 20th anniversary of Warsaw Ghetto Revolt.
1964 Soviet Anti-Semitism protested by JWB.
1964 Findings of JWB Young Adult Study made public.
1964 JWB Canal Zone Center aids refugees from Panama riots.
1964 Jewish chaplain and JWB supplies reach Vietnam.
1964 President Johnson says JWB and JCCs enrich American life.
1964 Ground broken for new Jerusalem YM-YWHA building.
1964 Florence G. Heller elected first woman President of JWB.
1965 JWB, Hillel and Council of Jewish Federations and Welfare Funds join forces in Conference on Jewish Young Adults.
1965 JWB launches two way exchange program between U.S. and Israeli social workers as 23 American JCC workers attend training seminar in Israel and Israeli workers are placed in American Centers.
1965 Jewish chaplain aids wounded as crisis erupts in Dominican Republic.
1965 JWB leaders participate in meetings with European Center leaders.